CHAPTER 6 I suppose you have heard the news, Basil?” said Lord Henry that evening as
hallwood was shown into a little private room at the Bristol where dinner had been laid for
three. “No, Harry,” answered the artist, giving his hat and coat to the bowing
waiter. “What is it? Nothing about politics, I hope! They don’t interest me. There is
hardly a single person in the House of Commons worth painting, though many of
them would be the better for a little whitewashing.” “Dorian Gray is engaged to
be married,” said Lord Henry, watching him as he spoke holwood started and then
frowned. “Dorian engaged to be married!” he cried.
“Impossible!” “It is perfectly true.” “To whom?” “To some little actress or other.” “I
can’t believe it. Dorian is far too sensible.” “Dorian is far too wise not to
do foolish things now and then, my dear Basil.” “Marriage is hardly a thing that one can
do now and then, Harry.” “Except in America,” rejoined Lord
Henry languidly. “But I didn’t say he was married. I said he was engaged to be
married. There is a great difference. I have a distinct remembrance of being
married, but I have no recollection at all of being engaged I'm inclined to
think that I never was engaged.” “But think of Dorian’s birth, and position, and
wealth. It would be absurd for him to marry so much beneath him.” “If you want to
make him marry this girl, tell him that, Basil he's sure to do it,
then. Whenever a man does a thoroughly stupid thing, it is always from the noblest
motives.” “I hope the girl is good, Harry. I don’t want to see Dorian tied to some
vile creature, who might degrade his nature and ruin his
intellect.” “Oh, she is better than good— —she is beautiful,” murmured Lord Henry, sipping
a glass glass of vermouth and orange bitters Dorian says she is beautiful, and
he is not often wrong about things of that kind. Your portrait of him has quickened
his appreciation of the personal appearance of other people. It has had
that excellent effect, amongst others. We are to see her tonight if that boy doesn’t forget his
appointment.” “Are you serious?” “Quite serious, Basil. I should be miserable if I thought
I should ever be more serious than I am am at the present
moment.” “But do you approve of it, Harry?” asked the painter, walking up and down
the room and biting his lip. “You can’t approve of it, possibly. It is some silly
infatuation.” “I never approve, or disapprove, of anything now. It is an
absurd attitude to take towards life. We are not sent into the world to he our moral
prejudices. I never take any notice of what common people say, and I never
interfere with what charming people do. If a personality fascinates me,
whatever mode of expression that personality selects is absolutely
delightful to me. Dorian Gray falls in love with a beautiful girl who acts
Juliet, and proposes to marry her. Why not?
If he wedded mesalina he would be none the less interesting. You know I'm not a champion
of marriage. The real drawback to marriage is that it makes one unselfish.
And unselfish people are colorless They lack individual uality Still, there are
certain temperaments that marriage makes more complex. They retain their egotism,
and add to it many other egos. They are forced to have more than one
life. They become more highly organized, and to be highly organized is, I should
fancy, the object of man’s existence. Besides, every experience is of
value, and whatever one may say against marriage, it is certainly an experience.
I hope that Dorian Gray will make this girl his wife, passionately adore her for
six months, and then suddenly become fascinated by someone else. He would be a wonderful
study.” “You don’t mean a single word of all that, Harry; you know you don’t. If
Dorian Gray’s life were spoiled, no one would be sorrier than yourself. You are
much better than you pretend to be.” Lord Henry laughed. “The reason we all
like to think so well of others is that we are all afraid for
ourselves. The basis of optimism is sheer terror. We think that we are generous
because we credit our neighbor with the possession of those virtues that are
likely to be a benefit to us. We praise the banker that we may overdraw our
account, and find good qualities in the Highwaymen in the hope that he may spare
our pockets. I mean everything that I have said. I have the greatest contempt
for optimism. As for a spoiled life, no life is spoiled but one whose growth is
arrested. If you want to mar a nature, you have merely to reform it. As for marriage,
of course that would be silly, but there are other and more interesting bonds
between men and women. I will certainly encourage them. They have the charm of being
fashionable. But here is Dorian himself.
He will tell you more than I can.” “My dear Harry, my dear
Basil, you must both congratulate me!” said the lad, throwing off his evening cape
with its satin lined wings and shaking each of his friends by the hand in
turn. “I have never been so happy. Of course, it is sudden— —all really delightful things
are. And yet it seems to me to be the one thing I been looking for all my
life.” He was flushed with excitement and pleasure, and looked extraordinarily
handsome. “I hope you will always be very happy, Dorian,” said hwood but I don’t
quite forgive you for not having let me know of your engagement. You let Harry
know.” “And I don’t forgive you for being late for dinner,” broke in Lord Henry,
putting his hand on the lad’s shoulder and smiling as he spoke. “Come, let us sit
down and try what the new chef here is like, and then you will tell us how it
all came about.” “There is really not much to tell,” cried Dorian as they took their seats at
the small round table. “What happened was simply this. After I left you yesterday
evening, Harry, I dressed, had some dinner at at that little Italian restaurant in
rert Street you introduced me to, and went down at 8:00 to the theater cibil was playing
Rosalind. Of course, the scenery was dreadful and the Orlando absurd. But
cibil You should have seen her! When she came on in her boy’s clothes, she was
perfectly wonderful. She wore a moss colored velvet jerkin with cinnamon
sleeves, slim, brown cross garded hose, a dainty little green cap with a hawk’s
feather caught in a jewel, and a hooded cloak lined with dull red. She had never
seemed to me more exquisite. She had all the delicate grace
of that Tanagra figurine that you have in your studio, Basil. Her hair clustered
around her face like dark leaves around a pale rose. As for her acting— —well, you shall
see her tonight She is simply a born artist. I sat in the dingy box absolutely
enthralled. I forgot that I was in London and in the 19th
century. I was away with my love in a forest that no man had ever
seen. After the performance was over, I went behind and spoke to her. As we were
sitting together, suddenly there came into her eyes a look that I had never
seen there before. My lips moved towards hers. We kissed each other. I can’t
describe to you what I felt at that moment. It seemed to me that all my life
had been narrowed to one perfect point of rose-colored joy. She trembled all
over and shook like a white narcissus. Then she flung herself on her knees and kissed my
hands. I feel that I should not tell you
all this, but I can’t help it. Of course, our engagement is a dead secret. She has
not even told her own mother. I don’t know what my guardians will say. Lord
Radley is sure to be furious. I don’t care.
I shall be of age in less than a year,
and then I can do what I like. I have
been right, Basil, haven’t I, to take my love out of poetry and to find my wife
in Shakespeare’s plays? Lips that Shakespeare taught to speak have whispered their secret in my
ear. I have had the arms of Rosalind around me, and kissed Juliet on the
mouth.” “Yes, Dorian, I suppose you were right,” said hallwood slowly. “Have you seen
her today asked Lord Henry. Dorian Gray shook his head. “I left her in the forest
of ardan I shall find her in an orchard in Verona.” Lord Henry sipped his
champagne in a meditative manner. “At what particular point did you mention the
word marriage, Dorian? And what did she say in answer? Perhaps you forgot all
about it and My dear Harry, I did not treat it as a business transaction, and I
did not make any formal proposal. I told her that I loved her, and she said she
was not worthy to be my wife. Not worthy!
Why, the whole world is nothing to me compared with her.” “Women are wonderfully practical,”
murmured Lord Henry, “much more practical than we are. In situations of that kind
we often forget to say anything about marriage, and they always remind us
hallwood laid his hand upon his arm.
“Don’t, Harry. You have annoyed Dorian. He is not like other men. He would never
bring misery upon anyone one. His nature is too fine for that.” Lord Henry looked
across the table. “Dorian is never annoyed with me,” he answered. “I asked the question
for the best reason possible, for the only reason, indeed, that excuses one for
asking any question— —simple curiosity. I have a theory that it is
always the women who propose to us, and not we who propose to the
women. Except, of course, in middleclass life. But then the middle class are not
modern.” Dorian Gray laughed, and tossed his head. “You are quite incourage Harry; but I
don’t mind. It is impossible to be angry with you. When you see cibil vain you
will feel that the man who could wrong her would be a beast, a beast without a
heart. I cannot understand how anyone can wish to shame the thing he loves. I love
cibil vain I want to place her on a pedestal of gold and to see the world
worship the woman who is mine. What is marriage? An irrevocable vow. You mocked
it for that. Ah! don’t mock. It is an irrevocable vow that I want to take. Her
trust makes me faithful, her belief makes me good. When I am with her, I regret all
that you have taught me. I become different from what you have known me to
be. I am changed, and the mere touch of cibil Vain's hand makes me forget you
and all your wrong, fascinating, poisonous, delightful
theories.” “And those are asked Lord Henry, helping himself to some
salad. “Oh, your theories about life, your theories about love, your theories about
pleasure. All your theories, in fact, Harry.” “Pleasure is the only thing worth
having a theory about,” he answered in his slow melodious voice. “But I'm afraid I
cannot claim my theory as my own. It belongs to Nature, not to me. Pleasure is
Nature’s test, her sign of approval. When we are happy, we are always good, but when
we are good, we are not always happy.” “Ah! but what do you mean by good?” cried Basil
hallwood Yes,” echoed Dorian, leaning back in his chair and looking at Lord Henry
over the heavy clusters of purple lipped irises that stood in the center of the
table, “what do you mean by good, Harry?” “To be good is to be in harmony with
oneself he replied, touching the thin stem of his glass with his pale fine
pointed fingers. “Discord is to be forced to be in harmony with others. One’s own
life— —that is the important thing. As for the lives of one’s
neighbors if one wishes to be a prig or a Puritan, one can flaunt one’s moral
views about them, but they are not one’s concern. Besides, individualism has really
the higher aim. Modern morality consists in accepting the standard of one’s age. I
consider that for any man of culture to accept the standard of his age is a form
of the grossest immorality.” “But, surely, if one lives merely for oneself Harry, one pays a
terrible price for doing so?” suggested the painter. “Yes, we are overcharged for
everything nowadays. I should fancy that the real tragedy of the poor is that
they can afford nothing but self-denial. Beautiful sins, like
beautiful things, are the privilege of the rich.” “One has to pay in other ways but
money.” “What sort of ways, Basil?” “Oh! I should fancy in
remorse, in suffering, in well, in the consciousness of degradation.” Lord Henry shrugged his
shoulders. “My dear fellow medieval art is charming, but medieval emotions are out
of date. One can use them in fiction, of course. But then the the only things that
one can use in fiction are the things that one has ceased to use in fact.
Believe me, no civilized man ever regrets a pleasure, and no uncivilized man ever
knows what a pleasure is.” “I know what pleasure is,” cried Dorian
Gray. “It is to adore someone That is certainly better than being adored,” he
answered, toying with some fruits. “Being adored is a nuisance. Women
treat us just as humanity treats its gods. They worship us, and are always B in
us to do something for them.” “I should have said that whatever
they asked for they had first given to us,” murmured the lad gravely. “They create love in our
natures. They have a right to demand it back.” “That is quite true, Dorian,” cried
hallwood Nothing is ever quite true,” said Lord Henry. “This is,” interrupted Dorian.
“You must admit, Harry, that women give to men the very gold of their
lives.” “Possibly,” he sighed, “but they invariably want it back in such very small
change. That is the worry. Women, as some witty Frenchmen once put it, inspire us
with the desire to do masterpieces and always prevent us from carrying them out.”
“Harry, you are dreadful! I don’t know why I like you so
much.” “You will always like me, Dorian,” he replied. “Will you have some coffee, you
fellows? Waiter, bring bring coffee, and fine champagne and some
cigarettes. No, don’t mind the cigarettes— —I have some. Basil, I can’t allow you to
smoke cigars. You must have a cigarette. A cigarette is the perfect type of a
perfect pleasure. It is exquisite, and it leaves one unsatisfied. What more can one want? Yes,
Dorian, you will always be fond of me. I represent to you all the sins you have
never had the courage to commit.” “What nonsense you talk, Harry!” cried the
lad, taking a light from a fire breathing silver dragon that the waiter had placed
on the table. “Let us go down to the theater When syil comes on the stage you
will have a new ideal of life. She will represent something to you that you have never
known.” “I have known everything,” said Lord Henry, with a tired look in his
eyes, “but I am always ready for a new emotion. I am afraid, however, that, for me
at any rate, there is no such thing. Still, your wonderful girl may thrill me. I love
acting. It is so much more real than life.
Let us go. Dorian, you will come with me I'm so sorry, Basil, but there is only
room for two in the brewham You must follow us in a
handsome They got up and put on their coats, sipping their coffee
standing. The painter was silent and preoccupied. There was a glue boom over
him. He could not bear this marriage, and yet it seemed to him to be better than
many other things that might have happened. After a few minutes, they all passed
downstairs. He drove off by himself, as had been arranged, and watched the
flashing lights of the little bofam in front of him. A strange sense of loss
came over him. He felt that Dorian Gray would never again be to him all that he
had been in the past. Life had come between them....
His eyes darkened, and the crowded flaring streets became blurred to his
eyes. When the cab drew up at the theater it seemed to him that he'd grown years
older. CHAPTER